Part 4. You will hear part of an ecology lecture about invasive species of plants and animals.
First, you have some time to look at questions 31 to 40.
Now listen carefully and answer questions 31 to 40.
Today I'm going to talk about invasive species. Let me start by saying what an invasive species
is and what it's not. Invasive species are any animal or plant that is introduced into
an environment by humans and which is then harmful to that environment.
It's important to be clear that not all introduced species are invasive.
Many introduced or non-native species thrive in new areas without posing any threat.
In some cases, invasive species have changed the natural world beyond recognition,
so let's look at the different ways they can be problematic.
First of all, invasive species may eat native species or sometimes they may bring a disease
with them which native species have never faced before and therefore have no defences against.
Often the invasive species breed very quickly, which further adds to the problem of native
species losing their sources of food. Species invasions are one of the biggest
causes of damage in an ecosystem, actually putting its survival at risk.
So how do invasive species spread? Without a doubt, the biggest cause is human activity.
This could be intentional or it could be accidental, such as when people who've been
on holiday in another country come back with, say, the seeds of plants on their clothes or shoes.
Plants and animals, especially insects, arrive in or on the cargo of ships and then escape into
their new home. But sometimes humans deliberately move animals and plants around the world,
for example, to use them to control pests on farms or to be pets. This can go very wrong
if those animals and plants move into wild settings and start breeding or begin growing
in ways that weren't predicted. Let's now look at an example of an
invasive species here in Australia. Rinella marina is a species of toad that was deliberately
introduced from Hawaii in 1935 as a form of biological control. It was hoped that the toads
would eat the grey-backed beetles responsible for destroying crops of sugar on many of the
plantations. At first, just a handful of toads were released by scientists into Queensland,
but this number soon grew as other states followed suit. Within two years, 62,000 young toads had
been released into the wild. The toads did nothing to protect the plantations, but they
did reproduce rapidly and could soon be found all over the northern half of the country.
The toads are poisonous at every stage of their life cycle, and anything that eats them will die.
My second example regarding invasive species is the United Kingdom. Actually, there are more than
3,000 invasive species there, including some that are extremely common. Some invasive plants,
such as Japanese knotweed, have had a devastating impact on parts of the UK.
Gardeners in the 19th century considered it a beautiful ornamental plant, which it is when
it's kept under control. But it soon spread into the countryside and remains a problem even to
this day as it's so hard to eradicate. Another invasive plant is rhododendrons,
which can be found in UK parks and woodlands. Their introduction dates back to 1763,
but they're now seen as harmful because they block out so much light that native wildflowers
can't grow beneath them. And then there are grey squirrels, which are one invasive species almost
everyone in the UK will have come across. But they're not the only invasive species
that we've come across. They were brought to the UK from North America and introduced to private
estates around the 1870s, but are now found everywhere, from forests to city squares.
Grey squirrels have outcompeted the smaller, native red squirrels. They both eat the same food,
carry a type of virus that is deadly to the red squirrels.
Red squirrel populations have collapsed, and there are only a handful of sites left in the UK
where they're found. An important question for ecologists worldwide is,
what can we do to tackle the problem of invasive species?
The first step in controlling invasive species is learning about the behaviour of new species
coming into the country. Monitoring is an important part of this, so that we can know
if the new species begins to have a negative impact in its new environment.
One effective way to keep track of invasive species is to create a database for the whole
country. That way, all relevant authorities and agencies can share important information
and take whatever actions needed. But the public also have a vital role to play in this process.
They should be encouraged to photograph harmful species, because this helps with identification,
and then to report when and where these were observed. But it's important to tell people
not to destroy or even touch what they've found. Now, I'm going to move on to an example...
That is the end of part four. You now have one minute to check your answers to part four.